<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>PAULA XML Documentation</title>
        <subtitle>Format version 1.1</subtitle>
        <releaseinfo>Version: P1.1.2013.1.21a</releaseinfo>
        <pubdate>21 Jan 2013</pubdate>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>            
                <personname>Amir Zeldes</personname>
                <email>amir.zeldes@rz.hu-berlin.de</email>
                
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>SFB 632 D1</orgname>
                    <orgdiv>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin </orgdiv>
                </affiliation>
                
            </author>
            <author>            
                <personname>Florian Zipser</personname>
                <email>f.zipser@gmx.de</email>
                
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>SFB 632 D1</orgname>
                    <orgdiv>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin </orgdiv>
                    <orgdiv>INRIA</orgdiv>
                </affiliation>
                
            </author>
            <author>            
                <personname>Arne Neumann</personname>
                <email>arne.neumann@uni-potsdam.de</email>
                
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>SFB 632 D1</orgname>
                    <orgdiv>Universität Potsdam</orgdiv>
                </affiliation>
                
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        
    </info>

        <preface><title>Preamble</title>
        <para>
            <firstterm>PAULA XML</firstterm> or <firstterm>PAULA</firstterm> for short
                (<firstterm>Potsdamer AUstauschformat Linguistischer Annotationen</firstterm>,
            'Potsdam Exchange Format for Linguistic Annotations') is a standoff XML format designed
            to represent a wide range of linguistically annotated textual and multi-modal corpora.
            The format was created at Potsdam University and developed within SFB 632, the
            collaborative research centre "Information Structure", subproject D1, "Linguistic
            Database" at Potsdam University and Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin (see
                <citation>Dipper2005</citation>, <citation>DipperGoetze2005</citation>,
                <citation>ChiarcosEtAl2008</citation>). The description below represents the
            normative documentation for PAULA version 1.1, with some notes on previous versions of
            PAULA. For the latest documentation always check the PAULA Website which also contains an online HTML version of this documentation. </para>
            <para>The standoff nature of PAULA refers to the fact that each layer of linguistic
            annotation, such as part-of-speech annotations, lemmatizations, syntax trees,
            coreference annotation etc. are stored in separate XML files which refer to the same raw
            data. In this manner annotations can easily be added, deleted and updated without
            disturbing independent annotation layers, and discontinuous or hierarchically
            conflicting structures can be represented. Additionally the format ensures the
            retainment of unaltered raw data, including white space and other elements often lost
            due to restrictions of the encoding format. As a generalized XML format, PAULA is
            indifferent to particular names or semantics of annotation structures. It concentrates
            instead on the representation of corpus data as a set of arbitrarily labeled directed
            acyclic graphs (so called multi-DAGs, wherein annotation projects may contain cycles as
            long as these are on different annotation levels).</para>
            <para>This documentation is structured as follows: the next chapter gives an overview of
            the overall <link xlink:href="#datamodel">data model</link> of the current PAULA format,
            followed by a chapter on <link xlink:href="#corpus_structure">corpus structure</link>
            for XML files and folders. Further chapters review different file types: the <link
                xlink:href="#required_files">minimal necessary files</link> for PAULA documents,
                <link xlink:href="#metadata">metadata</link>, <link xlink:href="#primary_text_data"
                >primary text data</link>, <link xlink:href="#tokenization">tokenizations</link> and
                <link xlink:href="#mark">span annotations</link>, <link xlink:href="#struct"
                >hierarchical graphs</link> and <link xlink:href="#pointing_relations">pointing
                relations</link>. The final chapters give additional information on the optional use
            of <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespaces</link>, some special scenarios such as
            building <link xlink:href="#parallel_corpora">parallel corpora</link>, <link
                xlink:href="#dialogue_data">dialogue corpora</link> and <link
                xlink:href="#multimodal">multimodal corpora</link>, recommendations for <link
                xlink:href="#naming_conventions">file naming conventions</link> and information on
                <link xlink:href="#versions">older/deprecated elements</link> of the PAULA XML
            standard focusing on differences to the current version.</para>
        </preface>
    <chapter xml:id="datamodel">
            <title>Datamodel overview</title>
  
                <para xlink:href="">PAULA projects are graphs dominated by a top level node refered
                to as a <link xlink:href="#corpus"><classname>corpus</classname></link>. Corpus
                objects comprise graphs of one or more annotated <link xlink:href="#document"
                        ><classname>document</classname></link> objects, optionally organized within
                a tree of <link xlink:href="#corpus"><classname>subcorpus</classname></link>
                objects. The tree of corpus, subcorpora and documents corresponds to a file system
                folder tree. Corpora, subcorpora and documents can all receive <link
                    xlink:href="#metadata"><classname>metadata</classname></link> annotations. </para>
            <para>All documents must contain at least one source of <link
                xlink:href="#primary_text_data"><classname>primary text data</classname></link>,
            possibly more in cases of <link xlink:href="#parallel_corpora">parallel corpora</link>
            or <link xlink:href="#dialogue_data">dialogue data</link>, and at least one <link
                xlink:href="#tokenization"><classname>tokenization</classname></link> of this data.
            Tokenized data may be annotated directly using features called <link xlink:href="#feat"
                    ><classname>feat</classname></link>, such as parts-of-speech, lemmatization,
            etc. Further hierarchical structures can be built on top of tokens using flat span
            objects called <link xlink:href="#mark"><classname>mark</classname></link> (i.e.
                <firstterm>markables</firstterm>) or hierarchically nestable objects called <link
                xlink:href="#struct"><classname>struct</classname></link> (i.e.
                <firstterm>structures</firstterm>), which may also be annotated with
                <classname>feat</classname> objects. The type of node or annotation (part-of-speech,
            phrase-category etc.) is given by the type attribute of each set of nodes or
            annotations. </para>
        <para>Beyond the edges resulting from the construction of hierarchies through structs,
            further non-hierarchical edges may be defined between any two nodes in a document using
            pointing relations. Both edges connecting structs to tokens or other structs and
            pointing relations may be annotated using feats and given a type. All objects and
            annotations below the document level may carry a PAULA <link xlink:href="#namespaces"
                    ><classname>namespace</classname></link> bundling relevant annotation layers
            which belong together under a common identifier (note that these are not identical with
            XML namespaces). The following two figures give an overview of this general data model
            for the corpus/document structure and the structure of objects within them. For details
            and examples of the individual model elements and their specific XML serialization see
            the next chapters.</para>
       
        <para>
            
            <figure xml:id="Figure_corpus_model">
                <title>Datamodel for (sub)corpus and document tree</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="figures/paula_corpusStructure.svg" scale="50"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="Figure_doc_model">
                <title>Datamodel for document-internal objects</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="figures/paula_documentStructure.svg" scale="30"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="corpus_structure">
        <title>Corpus structure</title>
        <sect1 xml:id="corpus">
            <title>Corpus and subcorpus</title>
            <para>In PAULA a corpus structure is defined by means of a file system folder structure.
                The name of the corpus is determined by the name of the top level directory of the
                folder structure. The top level directory may contain further directories. If these
                directories contain subdirectories themselves, then they are considered to be
                subcorpora. Subcorpora are generally used to provide meaningful subdivisions of a
                corpus, e.g. based on genre, period, language etc. These may be accompanied by
                appropriate <link xlink:href="#metadata">metadata</link>.</para>
            <para>Each subcorpus carries the name of its directory. It is possible, but not
                recommended, to repeat subcorpus names at different levels of nesting. A directory
                cannot contain two identically named subdirectories, and therefore it is impossible
                for two sibling subcorpora to have the same name. Under *NIX systems it is possible
                to have directories with identical names except for capitalization. This is not
                recommended for compatibility with other operating systems. In addition to
                directories, a top level corpus or a subcorpus may contain an
                    <classname>annoSet</classname> file, which lists the set of subfolders in the
                same directory (see <link xlink:href="#annoset">annoSets</link>). This is not
                required unless the corpus or subcorpus should receive metadata annotations (see
                    <link xlink:href="#metadata">metadata</link>).</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="Figure_paula_dir_struct">
                    <title>Directory structure for a PAULA corpus</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
+-- mycorpus/
¦   +-- subcorpus1/
¦   ¦   +-- doc1/
¦   ¦   +-- doc2/
¦   ¦   +-- doc3/
¦   +-- subcorpus2/
¦   ¦   +-- doc4/
¦   ¦   +-- doc5/
¦   ¦   +-- ...
¦   +-- subcorpus3/
... ...
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para> A subdirectory which contains no further directories is a document. Every corpus
                and subcorpus must contain at least one document (possibly nested within a lower
                level folder), empty corpora or subcorpora are not allowed. The minimal structure
                for a PAULA corpus is therefore a corpus folder containing a document folder, which
                must contain the minimal document structure described under <link
                    xlink:href="#document">documents</link>.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 xml:id="document">
            <title>Documents</title>
            <para>A PAULA <classname>document</classname> is a terminal directory within the
                directoy structure of the PAULA <classname><link xlink:href="#corpus"
                    >corpus</link></classname>, i.e. it is a folder that contains no subfolders.
                Usually documents corresponds to coherent texts (e.g. an article), but in some
                contexts other divisions may be sensible (e.g. chapters of a book as individual
                documents). The primary consideration is whether or not annotations need to cross
                boundaries between segments of the annotated texts, since annotation nodes and edges
                can only exist within a document. It is not possible for an element in one document
                to refer to or include an element from another document.</para>
            <para>The name of the document is determined by the name of the folder representing it.
                A document must contain at least a <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data"
                        >primary text data</link></classname> file, a <link
                    xlink:href="#tokenization"><classname>tokenization</classname></link>, an
                        <classname><link xlink:href="#annoset">annoSet</link></classname> file and
                the relevant <link xlink:href="#DTD">DTDs</link> used in the document, unless these
                are stored in a separate folder and refered to with appropriate relative paths. If
                the document contains no <link xlink:href="#tokenization">tokenization</link> or
                other annotations, then these will be <filename>paula_text.dtd</filename>,
                    <filename>paula_struct.dtd</filename> and <filename>paula_header.dtd</filename>.
                Typically, however, a document almost always contains a tokenization of the primary
                text data and some annotations, meaning at least <filename>paula_mark.dtd</filename>
                and <filename>paula_feat.dtd</filename> (see <link xlink:href="#DTD">DTDs</link> for
                more information). It is generally advisable to contain all DTDs used in a corpus in
                every document, as redundant DTDs do not disrupt processing or validation. </para>
            <para>By convention, all XML files within a document (i.e. all files except DTDs) share
                the document name as part of the file name, which appears first except for possible
                    <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespaces</link>, and is followed by annotation
                layer-specific elements. For more information about recommended naming practices see
                    <link xlink:href="#naming_conventions">naming conventions</link>.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 xml:id="annoset">
            <title>AnnoSets</title>
            <para>Each PAULA <classname><link xlink:href="#document">document</link></classname>
                must contain an <classname>annoSet</classname> file which describes the set of
                annotations contained in the document. The <classname>annoSet</classname> conforms
                with the <link xlink:href="#DTD">DTD</link>
                <filename>paula_struct.dtd</filename> and contains a
                    <classname>structList</classname> element which contains one or more
                    <classname>struct</classname> elements, each of which contains one or more
                    <classname>rel</classname> elements (these are the same elements used for the
                description of <link xlink:href="#struct">hierarchical annotations</link> as well).
                Every XML file within the document directory (but not DTDs and not the
                    <classname>annoSet</classname> file itself) must be the
                    <classname>@xlink:href</classname> attribute of some <classname>rel</classname>
                in the <classname>annoSet</classname>, including the special
                    <classname>annoFeat</classname> file if it has been included (see <link
                    xlink:href="#annofeat">Annofeats</link>). There are therefore as many
                    <classname>rel</classname> elements in the <classname>annoSet</classname> as
                there are XML files in the directory, minus one (since the
                    <classname>annoSet</classname> itself is not referenced). Different structs can
                be used to group together files belonging to one logical annotation layer, such as
                the <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data">primary text
                    data</link></classname> and its <classname><link xlink:href="#tokenization"
                        >tokenization</link></classname>, or related annotations such as part of
                speech and lemma. The following example shows some typical groupings following the
                PAULA <link xlink:href="#naming_conventions">naming conventions</link>.</para>
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_annoset">
                    <title>An <classname>annoSet</classname> file for doc1 in mycorpus</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_struct.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1.anno" />
 
<structList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="annoSet">
  <struct id="anno_1">
   <rel id="rel_1" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.anno_feat.xml" />
  </struct>
  <struct id="anno_2">
   <rel id="rel_2" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.text.xml" />
   <rel id="rel_3" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml" />
  </struct>
  <struct id="anno_3">
   <rel id="rel_4" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.tok_pos.xml" />
   <rel id="rel_5" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.tok_lemma.xml" />
  </struct>
  <struct id="anno_4">
   <rel id="rel_6" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.phrase.xml" />
   <rel id="rel_7" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.phrase_cat.xml" />
   <rel id="rel_8" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc1.phrase_func.xml" />
  </struct>
 </structList>

</paula>]]></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>Annotation layers within the same struct are often interdependent, such that
                removing one of the files from the document may disrupt the annotation graph shared
                with the others. Also note that since <link xlink:href="#namespaces"
                    >namespaces</link> are also used to group related annotation layers together,
                often (but not necessarily always) layers with the same namespace will also be in
                the same <classname>struct</classname> in the <classname>annoSet</classname>.</para>
            <para>A second function of annoSets is to list the contents of corpora or subcorpora.
                AnnoSets within subcorpus or corpus folders are optional, though if they are
                missing, the contents of the folder cannot be validated against a list. AnnoSets in
                corpora or subcorpora are only required if the corpus or subcorpus should receive
                metadata annotations, in which case an <classname>annoSet</classname> to which the
                metadata features must point is required (see <link xlink:href="#metadata"
                    >metadata</link> for more information). An <classname>annoSet</classname> for a
                subcorpus or corpus can look like the following example.</para>
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_annoset_corpus">
                    <title>An <classname>annoSet</classname> file for the corpus
                            <filename>mycorpus</filename> with three documents</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_struct.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.anno" />
 
<structList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="annoSet">
  <struct id="anno_1">
   <rel id="rel_1" xlink:href="doc1/" />
   <rel id="rel_2" xlink:href="doc2/" />
   <rel id="rel_3" xlink:href="doc3/" />
  </struct>
 </structList>

</paula>]]></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>Corpus or subcorpus annoSets generally place all child subcorpora or documents
                within one <classname>struct</classname> element as in the example above, though it
                is not prohibited to group some items into different <classname>struct</classname>
                elements. It is also possible to mix subcorpora and documents within the same corpus
                or subcorpus level folder. There is no difference in notation and all immediate
                subfolders in the file system are simply listed: <filename>subcorpus1/</filename>,
                    <filename>doc1/</filename> etc.</para>
        </sect1>
    </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="required_files">
        <title>Required files and DTDs</title>
            <sect1><title>Minimal document structure</title>
        <para> Every document within a PAULA corpus requires at least one instance of each of the
            following three XML file types: a <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data"
                    >primary text data</link></classname> file, a <link xlink:href="#tokenization"
                    ><classname>tokenization</classname></link>, and an <classname><link
                    xlink:href="#annoset">annoSet</link></classname> file. These accordingly define
            the raw data, a basic segmentation of the data into minimal units and a list of the
            files in the directory (see documentation of the individual file types for
            details).</para>
        <para>Additionally, the relevant DTDs must be added which define these file types. At a
                minimum, the DTDs necessary for the required files above are: </para>
        <para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><filename>paula_header.dtd</filename></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><filename>paula_struct.dtd</filename></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><filename>paula_mark.dtd</filename></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><filename>paula_text.dtd</filename></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
                <para>The DTDs may be repeated in each document to simplify moving and adding documents at any point in the corpus strucutre (as in the examples in this documentation), 
                    or else DTDs can be saved in one folder (e.g. the corpus root) and refered to from each document using a relative path.</para>
            </sect1>
                <sect1 xml:id="DTD"><title>Additional DTDs</title>
                    <para>Beyond the DTDs in the previous section, if the document contains any
                        <classname><link xlink:href="#feat">feat</link></classname> annotations or
                an <classname><link xlink:href="#annofeat">annoFeat</link></classname> file, it will
                require the DTD <filename>paula_feat.dtd</filename>, and if it contains <link
                    xlink:href="#pointing_relations">pointing relations</link> using the
                    <classname>rel</classname> element, the file <filename>paula_rel.dtd</filename>
                will also be necessary. A further DTD, <filename>paula_multiFeat.dtd</filename>, is
                needed if multiple feat annotations should be defined in one XML file, see <link
                    xlink:href="#multifeats">multifeats</link>.</para>
            <para>Usually the necessary DTDs are repeatedly included in every document folder for
                validation purposes, though it is possible to include them in only one folder and
                refer to them from each document using a relative path (cf. the previous section).
                It is not necessary to include <filename>paula_rel.dtd</filename> or
                    <filename>paula_feat.dtd</filename> for corpora or documents that do not contain
                pointing relations, even if some other documents in the corpus do, though it may be
                recommended to have the same DTDs or DTD references in all folders in case pointing
                relations or feature annotations are added to further corpus documents later on. The
                following full list of DTDs may therefore be included in every document:</para>
                    <para><itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><filename>paula_header.dtd</filename></para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><filename>paula_struct.dtd</filename></para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><filename>paula_mark.dtd</filename></para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                        <para><filename>paula_text.dtd</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>paula_feat.dtd</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>paula_rel.dtd</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>paula_multiFeat.dtd</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
            </sect1>
    </chapter>
        
        <chapter xml:id="metadata">
            <title>Metadata</title>
            <para>Metadata encompasses annotations that apply to an entire object in the corpus
            structure, i.e. to a corpus, subcorpus or document. The metadata does not annotate
            specific elements within a text, but rather characterizes the entire container object.
            In PAULA XML metadata is realized in lists of <classname>feat</classname> elements
            (features), which refer to the <classname>annoSet</classname> of the relevant object
            (see <link xlink:href="#annoset">annoSets</link>). It is also possible for metadata
            annotations to carry a <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespace</link>, just like any
            other form of annotation. </para>
            <sect1>
                <title>Corpus and subcorpus metadata</title>
                <para>Corpus and subcorpus level metadata can optionally be added to any corpus or
                subfolder containing an <classname><link xlink:href="#annoset"
                    >annoSet</link></classname>. It is not possible to add metadata to a folder not
                containing an <classname>annoSet</classname>. The following example illustrates a
                metadata annotation for the corpus <filename>mycorpus</filename>.</para>
                
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_corp_meta"><title>Metadata for the corpus <filename>mycorpus</filename></title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.meta_lang"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="lang" xml:base="mycorpus.anno.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#anno_1" value="eng"/><!-- English -->
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>Since the name of the metadata attribute is determined in the the
                        <classname>@type</classname> attribute of the
                        <classname>featList</classname> element, it is necessary to define a
                    separate <classname>feat</classname> file for each metadata annotation, unless
                        <link xlink:href="#meta_multifeat">multiFeat</link> metadata files are used.
                    Note also that in this example the feat is only pointing at the
                        <classname>struct</classname> element "anno_1" from the
                        <classname>annoSet</classname> file <filename>mycorpus.anno.xml</filename>.
                    It is also possible to have multiple <classname>feat</classname> elements,
                    pointing to each one of the <classname>struct</classname> elements in the
                        <classname>annoSet</classname>. In the current version of PAULA this makes
                    no difference: once a metadata annotation has been applied to any
                        <classname>struct</classname> element in the <classname>annoSet</classname>,
                    it applies to the entire object described by the
                    <classname>annoSet</classname>.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Document metadata</title>
                <para>Document metadata works exactly like corpus metadata: it is defined within a
                        <classname>feat</classname> file which has the annotation name in the
                        <classname>featList</classname>
                    <classname>@type</classname> attribute and the value in the
                        <classname>feat</classname>
                    <classname>@value</classname> attribute. The <classname>feat</classname> element
                    should point at a <classname>struct</classname> element from the document's
                            <classname><link xlink:href="#annoset">annoSet</link></classname>. It is
                    possible but not necessary to annotate all <classname>struct</classname>
                    elements in the <classname>annoSet</classname>. The following example
                    demonstrates this.</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_doc_meta"><title>Metadata for the document <filename>mycorpus/doc1</filename></title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1.meta_year"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="year" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.anno.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#anno_1" value="1999"/><!-- year 1999 -->
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>If the <classname>annoSet</classname> of doc1 contains several structs names
                    "anno_1", "anno_2" etc., it is possible to annotate them all using multiple
                        <classname>feat</classname> elements. This is identical to annotating just
                    one of the elements, as in the example above: the metadata annotation "year" has
                    been applied to the document and given the value "1999".</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 xml:id="meta_multifeat">
                <title>Using multifeats in metadata</title>
                <para>When using a large number of metadata annotations, it is sometimes more
                    convenient to use just one XML document to define all meta annotations. This is
                    made possible by using <classname>multiFeat</classname> files. The following
                    example illustrates the use of <classname>multiFeat</classname> annotations to
                    define metadata. For more detailed information on
                        <classname>multiFeat</classname> annotations see also <link
                        xlink:href="#multifeats">multiFeat annotations</link>.</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_meta_multiFeat"><title>Multiple metadata annotations in one file using <classname>multiFeat</classname> elements.
                    </title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_multiFeat.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1.meta_multiFeat"/>
    
<multiFeatList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="multiFeat" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.anno.xml">

    <multiFeat xlink:href="#anno_1"> 
        <feat name="year" value="2012"/>
        <feat name="language" value="English"/>
        <feat name="source_format" value="PAULA XML"/>
        <!-- ... -->
    </multiFeat>
  
</multiFeatList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 xml:id="annofeat">
                <title>AnnoFeats</title>
                <para>Each PAULA document may optionally contain an <classname>annoFeat</classname> file
                    listing the types of all annotation files including <classname>mark</classname>,
                    <classname>feat</classname>, <classname>struct</classname> and
                    <classname>rel</classname> files, for validation purposes. Not including an
                    <classname>annofeat</classname> file means that the annotation layers available
                    within the files specified in the <classname>annoSet</classname> cannot be
                    validated, though it may make it easier to update annotation layers dynamically. The
                    following example illustrates the use of the <classname>annoFeat</classname> file in
                    reference to <xref linkend="Example_annoset"/> in the previous section. </para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_annofeat">
                        <title>An <classname>annoFeat</classname> file for doc1 in mycorpus</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
 <header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1.annoFeat" />
 <featList type="annoFeat" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.anno.xml" 
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_1" value="annoFeat" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_2" value="text" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_3" value="tok" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_4" value="pos" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_5" value="lemma" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_6" value="phrase" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_7" value="cat" />
  <feat xlink:href="#rel_8" value="func" />
 </featList>

</paula>]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>Note that since the value of the <classname>feat</classname> is a string and not
                    an ID, it is possible for multiple rels to refer to the same annotation type name.
                    In order to disambiguate in such cases, it is possible to use <link
                        xlink:href="#namespaces">namespaces</link>, provided that these have been used
                    in the corresponding annotation files. The value then takes the form
                    "namespace:anno_name", e.g. "stts:pos".</para>
                <para>The <classname>annoFeat</classname> file cannot be used in corpus and subcorpus
                    directories.</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="primary_text_data">
            <title>Primary text data</title>
            <para>The <classname>primary text data</classname> forms the lowest level of resource
                representation, corresponding to the minimally analyzed linguistic data: a strech of
                untokenized plain text. The presence of at least one such file is obligatory in
                every PAULA <classname><link xlink:href="#document">document</link></classname>.
                Even if the resource to be annotated originates in spoken data for which a primary
                recording exists, its textual transcription forms the primary data. A segment of a
                recording is therefore seen to 'take place' in correspondences with a certain
                stretch of text (see <link xlink:href="#AV_data">Aligned audio/video files</link>
                for details). The primary data follows the schema definition in <filename><link
                        xlink:href="#req_XML">paula_text.dtd</link></filename>, which must be
                present. The type of the file is "text", and by convention the file name ends with
                the extension <filename>*.text.xml</filename> and its paula_id is the same as the
                file name prefix, ending in <code>_text</code> instead of the file extension
                    <filename>*.text.xml</filename>. <xref linkend="Example_text"/> illustrates a
                    <classname>primary text data</classname> file called
                    <filename>mycorpus.doc1.text.xml</filename>.</para>
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_text"><title>A primary text data file</title><programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_text.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_text" type="text"/>

<body>This is an example.</body>

</paula>]]></programlisting></example>
            </para>
            <para>A PAULA document can also contain more than one <classname>primary text
                data</classname> file. There are at least two scenarios where this is recommended,
            for which the respective sections should be consulted: <link
                xlink:href="#parallel_corpora">parallel corpora</link> with aligned texts in
            multiple languages and <link xlink:href="#dialogue_data">dialogue data</link> with
            multiple simultaneous speakers.</para>
            <para>As with other PAULA XML files, the first segment of text before a period within
                the filename of the <classname>primary text data</classname> file can be interpreted
                as a PAULA <classname><link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespace</link></classname>.
                In documents with only one such file, this is usually not important, but it is
                possible to use namespaces to group together text from different languages or
                speakers in parallel corpora or dialogue data respectively. </para>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="mark">
            <title>Spans and markables</title>
            <sect1><title>Introduction to spans and markables</title>
            <para> In PAULA it is possible to define spans of data for further annotation. Spans are
                    defined using the <classname>mark</classname> element, which stands for
                        <firstterm>markable</firstterm> and has two primary functions: defining a
                            <link xlink:href="#tokenization"
                        >tokenization</link> for a primary text data and defining a
                    non-terminal <link xlink:href="#span_anno">annotation span</link> node above the token
                    level. </para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 xml:id="tokenization"><title>Tokenizations and token markables</title>
            <para>A <classname>tokenization</classname> forms a minimal level
                    of analysis that segments a <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data"
                            >primary text data</link></classname> file into units that can be
                    annotated further. It is not possible to directly annotate text that is not
                    tokenized, and every PAULA document must contain at least one
                        <classname>tokenization</classname>. It is possible to include whitespace
                    characters within the primary data and then ignore these characters while
                    tokenizing, so that adjacent tokens are not interrupted by any characters on the
                    tokenized level. <xref linkend="Example_tok"/> illustrates this
                    principle.</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_tok"><title>Tokenization of the <classname>primary text data</classname> "This is an example."</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_mark.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_tok"/>

<markList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="tok" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.text.xml">
 <mark id="tok_1" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',1,4))"/><!-- This -->
 <mark id="tok_2" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',6,2))"/><!-- is -->
 <mark id="tok_3" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',9,2))"/><!-- an -->
 <mark id="tok_4" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',12,7))"/><!--example-->
 <mark id="tok_5" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',19,1))"/><!-- . -->
</markList>
</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>The first token element with the id "tok_1" begins at the first character of
                the text (the letter "T") and goes covering a total of 4 character: "This".
                Character 5 is a space, which has not been tokenized. The next token, "tok_2",
                begins at character 6, covering 2 characters: "is". It is also possible to define
                tokens with no textual extension, i.e. empty tokens. Such tokens have a string range
                spanning zero characters. However, they must still have an anchor position within
                the text. The following example illustrates an empty token in the sentence "he takes
                people out to fish", where the unrealized subject of "to fish" is tokenized between
                "out" and "to" with a character span of zero characters.</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_tok_fish"><title>Tokenization of the primary data "he takes people out to fish"</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_mark.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc2_tok"/>

<markList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="tok" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc2.text.xml">
<mark id="tok_1" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',1,2))"/><!-- he -->
<mark id="tok_2" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',4,5))"/><!-- takes -->
<mark id="tok_3" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',10,6))"/><!--people-->
<mark id="tok_4" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',17,3))"/><!-- out -->
<mark id="tok_5" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',21,0))"/><!--   -->
<mark id="tok_6" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',22,2))"/><!-- to -->
<mark id="tok_7" 
 xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',25,4))"/><!--fish-->
</markList>
</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>Although a PAULA tokenization file is defined with reference to the general
                    markable DTD <filename><link xlink:href="#DTD">paula_mark.dtd</link></filename>, it is distinguished from other types
                    of markables, specifically <link xlink:href="#span_anno">annotation
                        markables</link>, in two ways. Firstly, the <classname>@type</classname>
                    attribute of the element <classname>markList</classname>, which must be set to
                    the value <classname>tok</classname>. Secondly, tokenization can only refer to a
                        <classname>primary text data</classname> file. It is not possible to define
                    a token pointing to a more complex structure (e.g. another markable or
                    token).</para>
                <para>As of PAULA version 1.1 it is possible to have multiple <classname>primary
                        text data</classname> files, each of which must then be tokenized. Multiple
                    tokenizations of the same <classname>primary text data</classname> are not
                    possible in PAULA 1.1, but are planned as part of a future version of PAULA XML. </para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 xml:id="span_anno"><title>Annotation span markables</title>
                <para>The element <classname>mark</classname> may be used to group together a set of
                    <link xlink:href="#tokenization">tokens</link> for further annotation. This is
                usually done in order to annotate a certain feature-value pair which applies to
                these tokens. Span annotations therefore have the semantics of
                    <firstterm>attribution</firstterm> within the graph structure, i.e. stating that
                an area of the data has a certain property or attribute. These attributes are
                realized in PAULA using <classname><link xlink:href="#feat">feat</link></classname>
                annotation files, one or more of which can apply to any span defined by a markable.
                Span markables are defined with reference to the DTD <filename><link
                        xlink:href="#DTD">paula_mark.dtd</link></filename>. The type of markable
                being annotated (e.g. a referent or referring expression in a discourse, a chunk for
                chunking annotation, etc.) is given by the <classname>@type</classname> attribute of
                the <classname>markList</classname> element, and may be any string value other than
                "tok" which is reserved for <link xlink:href="#tokenization">tokenizations</link>.
                Other values are not ruled out by the format, but it is recommended to use types
                that follow XML element naming conventions, i.e. strings that contain only
                alphanumeric ascii characters with no spaces and beginning with an alphabetic
                character.</para>
                <para>Markables may be continuous or discontinuous, i.e. they may apply to a set of
                    consecutive tokens or to non-consecutive tokens. The following example
                    illustrates both types of markables in a single file with the type
                    "chunk".</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_mark"><title>Markables of the type "chunk" above a set of six tokens "I" "'ve "picked" "the" "kids" "up"</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_mark.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_chunk_seg"/>

<markList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="chunk" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml">
 <!-- I -->
 <mark id="chunk_1" xlink:href="#tok_1"/>
 <!-- 've picked...up -->
 <mark id="chunk_2" 
  xlink:href="(#xpointer(id('tok_2')/range-to(id('tok_3'))),#tok_6)"/>
 <!-- the kids -->
 <mark id="chunk_3" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(id('tok_3')/range-to(id('tok_4')))"/>
</markList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>In the example, three markables have been defined which refer to six tokens in
                the token file <classname>mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml</classname>, as entered in the
                    <classname>markList</classname> element's <classname>@xml:base</classname>
                attribute. The first markable, "chunk_1" points to "#tok_1" in the token file which
                covers the string "I". The third markable, "chunk_3", points to a range of
                consecutive tokens, from "tok_3" to "tok_4", which covers the words "the kids". The
                chunk in the middle, "chunk_2", points to a discontinuous set of tokens, namely a
                range "tok_2" to "tok_3" and a further individual token "tok_6", corresponding to
                the tokens "'ve picked" and a later token "up". These markables cannot be annotated
                further within this file (e.g. with the type of chunk as nominal, verbal, etc.).
                Further annotation of the markables beyond the markable list
                    <classname>@type</classname> must be added in separate files as <classname><link
                        xlink:href="#feat">feat</link></classname> annotations.</para>
                <para>Note that the markable type is set once in the <classname>markList</classname>
                    element for all markables in the file. To define markables of a different type,
                    a separate markable file must be generated. Separate files are not required to
                    have the same segmentations and constitute independent layers of
                    annotation.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 xml:id="feat"><title>Feats</title>
                <para>The element <classname>feat</classname> and corresponding feat files represent
                    arbitrary key-value feature annotations which may be applied to a variety of
                    elements, such as parts of speech or syntactic categories, but also metadata.
                    They can be applied to mark elements to annotate <link xlink:href="#span_anno"
                        >spans of tokens</link> or even <link xlink:href="#tokenization"
                        >tokens</link> directly, but also to <link xlink:href="#struct"
                            ><classname>struct</classname></link> elements as part of
                    non-hierarchical annotations or metadata annotation of <classname><link
                            xlink:href="#annoset">annoSet</link></classname> elements. The following
                    two examples illustrate feature annotation of spans and tokens. For other uses
                    see <link xlink:href="#metadata">metadata</link> and <link
                        xlink:href="#struct_feat">annotating structs</link>. In <xref
                        linkend="Example_tok_feat"/> a <classname>featList</classname> with the
                        <classname>@type</classname> "pos" contains six <classname>feat</classname>
                    elements, each annotating a single token with its part of speech in the
                        <classname>@value</classname> attribute. </para>
             <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_tok_feat"><title>Annotating tokens with <classname>feat</classname> annotations for part of speech</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_pos"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="pos" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#tok_1" value="PP"/><!-- I -->
    <feat xlink:href="#tok_2" value="VBP"/><!-- 've -->
    <feat xlink:href="#tok_3" value="VBN"/><!-- picked -->
    <feat xlink:href="#tok_4" value="DT"/><!-- the -->
    <feat xlink:href="#tok_5" value="NNS"/><!-- kids -->
    <feat xlink:href="#tok_6" value="RP"/><!-- up -->
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
             </para>
                
                <para>It is also possible to annotate more than one token at a time by using <link
                        xlink:href="#span_anno">annotation span markables</link>, which cover one or
                    more tokens each. In this case the features do not refer to a token file, but to
                    a markable file which refers to some tokens in itself. The following example
                    illustrates the annotation of such spans, which works in much the same way as
                    the annotation of tokens.</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_mark_feat"><title>Annotating spans from a markable file with <classname>feat</classname> annotations for chunk
                            type</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_chunk_seg_chunk_type"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="chunk_type" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.chunk_seg.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#chunk_1" value="N"/><!-- I -->
    <feat xlink:href="#chunk_2" value="V"/><!-- 've picked _ up -->
    <feat xlink:href="#chunk_3" value="N"/><!-- the kids -->
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>In this case, three features of the type "chunk_type" have been assigned to
                    three markables in the file <filename>mycorpus.doc1.chunk_seg.xml</filename>.
                    The "chunk_type" of the first markable is given the value "N". The second
                    markable receives the "chunk_type" "V" and the third is "N" again. Note that the
                    tokens covered by the respective markables are not defined here, though comments
                    to the right of each element can help keep track of the text covered by each
                    annotation. The actual tokens covered by each markable are defined in the
                    separate file <filename>mycorpus.doc1.chunk_seg.xml</filename>. There is also no
                    necessary connection between the type of feature and the type of markable,
                    though in many cases it makes sense to give them similar names, e.g. markables
                    called "chunk" and an annotation "chunk_type" (see also <link
                        xlink:href="#naming_conventions">naming conventions</link>).</para>
                
            </sect1>
            <sect1><title xml:id="multifeats">Multifeats</title>
                <para> In cases where multiple annotations always apply to the same nodes, it may be
                    more economic to specify multiple, usually related annotations in the same file.
                    This is made possible by the use of <classname>multiFeat</classname> files,
                    together with the associated <filename>paula_multiFeat.dtd</filename>. Each
                    multiFeat contains multiple feat annotations applying to the element specified
                    in the <classname>@xlink:href</classname> attribute of the
                        <classname>multiFeat</classname> element. Since the
                        <classname>multiFeat</classname> itself is not an actual annotation, but a
                    container for other annotations, the <classname>multiFeatList</classname>
                    element is conventionally given the type "multiFeat". The example below
                    illustrates the use of multiFeat annotations. </para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_multiFeat"><title>Annotating multiple annotations using <classname>multiFeat</classname> elements.
                        </title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_multiFeat.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1.tok_multiFeat"/>
    
<multiFeatList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="multiFeat" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml">

    <multiFeat xlink:href="#tok_1"> <!-- I -->
        <feat name="pos" value="PPER"/>
        <feat name="lemma" value="I"/>
    </multiFeat>
    <multiFeat xlink:href="#tok_2"> <!-- 've -->
        <feat name="pos" value="VBP"/> 
        <feat name="lemma" value="have"/>
    </multiFeat>
    <!-- ... -->
   
</multiFeatList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para> Note that there is no difference from the data model point of view between
                    the use of multiple <classname>feat</classname> files or one
                        <classname>multiFeat</classname> file specifying the same annotation types.
                    Note also that when using <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespaces</link>, all
                    annotations in a <classname>multiFeat</classname> have the same namespace,
                    determined by the <classname>multiFeat</classname> file name. While it is
                    possible to have different annotation in different
                        <classname>multiFeat</classname> elements in the same file, it is
                    recommended to avoid this, as it can quickly become confusing. The use of
                        <classname>multiFeat</classname> annotations can also make it potentially
                    difficult to add, remove and edit annotations after the fact, since separate
                    annotation layers are mixed in one XML file.</para>
                
            </sect1>
            
            
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Hierarchical structures</title>
            <para>Hierarchical structures are used in PAULA for two different purposes: for the
                creation of hierarchically nested annotation graphs (e.g. syntax trees, rhetorical
                structure annotation, hierarchical topological fields) and for the definition of
                structured <classname>annoSet</classname> objects (see <link xlink:href="#annoset"
                    >annoSets</link>). Hierarchical structures express the graph semantic property
                that a parent node <firstterm>consists of</firstterm> its children, or in reverse,
                that children nodes <firstterm>constitute</firstterm> their parent nodes. The
                semantics of hierarchical edges is also called <firstterm>dominance</firstterm> (a
                parent node <firstterm>dominates</firstterm> a child node), and they are
                consequently known as <firstterm>dominance edges</firstterm> as well. This chapter
                describes hierarchical annotation graphs. For non-hierarchical annotations see also
                    <link xlink:href="#mark">spans and markables</link>. </para>
            <sect1 xml:id="struct"><title>Structs</title>
                <para>To form hierarchically nested (i.e. recursive) non-terminal nodes above the
                    token level, the <classname>struct</classname> element should be used.
                        <firstterm>Directed acyclic graphs</firstterm> (DAGs) of struct elements may
                    be defined in struct files according to <filename><link xlink:href="#DTD"
                            >paula_struct.dtd</link></filename>. The <classname>struct</classname>
                    element is embedded within a <classname>structList</classname> which determines
                    the <classname>@type</classname> for all structs in the file. It has only one
                    attribute, an <classname>@id</classname> which allows it to become the target of
                    incoming edges. Outgoing edges are annotated using the child element
                        <classname>rel</classname>, which has its own <classname>@type</classname>
                    (the type of edge) and an attribute <classname>@xlink:href</classname>
                    determining the target's id, as well as its own <classname>@id</classname>
                    attribute for further annotation (see annotating structs and rels). The
                    following example illustrates a simple syntax tree for the sentence "he ". The
                    correpsonding syntax tree is also visualized in <xref linkend="Figure_fish_tree"
                    />. </para>
                
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_struct"><title>Constructing a hierarchical syntax tree with <classname>struct</classname> elements
                        type</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_struct.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc2_phrase"/>

<structList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="phrase">
<struct id="phrase_1"> <!-- NP -->
 <!-- he -->
 <rel id="rel_1" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_1"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_2"> <!-- VP -->
 <!-- takes -->
 <rel id="rel_2" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_2"/>
 <rel id="rel_3" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_3"/>
 <rel id="rel_4" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_4"/>
 <rel id="rel_5" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_5"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_3"> <!-- NP -->
 <!-- people -->
 <rel id="rel_6" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_3"/>
 <!-- _ -->
 <rel id="rel_7" type="secedge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_5"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_4"> <!-- PRT -->
 <!-- out -->
 <rel id="rel_8" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_4"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_5"> <!-- S -->
 <rel id="rel_9" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_6"/>
 <rel id="rel_10" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_7"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_6"> <!-- NP -->
 <!-- _ -->
 <rel id="rel_11" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_5"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_7"> <!-- VP -->
 <!-- to -->
 <rel id="rel_12" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_6"/>
 <rel id="rel_13" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_8"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_8"> <!-- VP -->
 <!-- fish -->
 <rel id="rel_14" type="edge" xlink:href="mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_7"/>
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_9"> <!-- S -->
 <rel id="rel_15" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_1"/> 
 <rel id="rel_16" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_2"/> 
</struct>
<struct id="phrase_10"> <!-- TOP -->
 <rel id="rel_17" type="edge" xlink:href="#phrase_9"/> 
</struct>
</structList>

</paula>

]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>
                    
                    <figure xml:id="Figure_fish_tree">
                        <title>Syntax tree for "he takes people out to fish"</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="figures/fish_tree.png" scale="60"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
                
                <para>In this example, the individual nodes in the tree from the figure above are
                    represented by <classname>struct</classname> elements. Each
                        <classname>struct</classname> element contains <classname>rel</classname>
                    elements which define edge leading to its children. Thus "phrase_1" directly
                    dominates a token "tok_1", corresponding to the word "he". Note that, since the
                    tokens are in a separate file, references to the tokens give a full href
                    attribute with the token file name: mycorpus.doc2.tok.xml#tok_1. Phrase nodes
                    dominating other phrase nodes within the same file do not require any prefix:
                    "phrase_9" dominates "#phrase_5" directly. Most edges in the tree have been
                    given the edge <classname>@type</classname> "edge", but one edge, by which the
                    NP above "people" (marked in red in the figure above) indirectly dominates an
                    empty token between "out" and "to" (marked in green) with a different
                        <classname>@type</classname>: "secedge" (a 'secondary' edge). There is no
                    limit to the amount of edge types used in a document, but XML naming conventions
                    should be followed in giving type names that are ascii alphanumeric, without
                    spaces and beginning with an alphabetic character (see <link
                        xlink:href="#naming_conventions">naming conventions</link>). The node labels
                    ("NP", "VP") and the edge labels ("SBJ", "PRP") are not defined within the
                        <classname>struct</classname> file, but are given as separate annotation
                    files: see <link xlink:href="#struct_feat">annotating structs and
                    rels</link>.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 xml:id="struct_feat"><title>Annotating structs and rels</title>
                <para>Hierarchical graphs made of <classname>struct</classname> and
                        <classname>rel</classname> elements may be further annotated using
                        <classname>feat</classname> elements, much like annotation <link
                        xlink:href="#span_anno">spans</link>. To annotate
                        <classname>struct</classname> nodes, use a <classname>feat</classname> file
                    pointing to the nodes and give the annotation name in the
                        <classname>@type</classname> attribute. The following example illustrates
                    the phrase annotations for the tree in <xref linkend="Example_struct"/> in the previous section.</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_struct_feat"><title>Annotating nodes from a <classname>struct</classname> file with <classname>feat</classname>
                        annotations for phrase category: "cat"</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc2_phrase_cat"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="cat" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc2.phrase.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_1" value="NP"/><!-- he -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_2" value="VP"/><!-- takes -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_3" value="NP"/><!-- people _ -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_4" value="PRT"/><!-- out -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_5" value="S"/><!-- _ to fish -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_6" value="NP"/><!-- _ -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_7" value="VP"/><!-- to fish -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_8" value="VP"/><!-- fish -->
    <!-- he takes people out _ to fish -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_9" value="S"/>
    <!-- he takes people out _ to fish -->
    <feat xlink:href="#phrase_10" value="TOP"/>
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>The annotation name is set as "cat" and it applies to the elements "phrase_1"
                    to "phrase_10" in the xml:base file, which contains the phrase nodes. For
                    conventions how to name the <classname>@paula_id</classname> and XML files, see
                        <link xlink:href="#naming_conventions">naming conventions</link>.</para>
                <para>Annotating edges works in a similar way, except that
                        <classname>rel</classname> elements are references instead of
                        <classname>struct</classname> elements. It is possible to annotate edges of
                    multiple types in the same XML file, as long as the name of the annotation being
                    applied to them is identical. The following example illustrates this using the
                    edges from <xref linkend="Example_struct"/> in the preivous section (note that
                    "rel_7" had the type "secedge" while the others had "edge", and also that not
                    all edges have been annotated, which is fine).</para>
                <para>
                    <example xml:id="Example_rel_feat"><title>Annotating edges from a <classname>struct</classname> file with <classname>feat</classname>
                        annotations for phrase function: "func"</title>
                        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc2_phrase_func"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="func" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc2.phrase.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_5" value="PRP"/><!-- _ to fish -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_9" value="SBJ"/><!-- _ -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_11" value="NONE"/><!-- _ -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_15" value="SBJ"/><!-- he -->
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                    </example>
                </para>
                <para>Just as with markables, it is also possible to specify multiple annotations
                    for the same nodes in one XML document using multiFeat files (see <link
                        xlink:href="#multifeats">multiFeats</link> for details).</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="pointing_relations">
            <title>Pointing relations</title>
            <para>Pointing relations are ahierarchical edges between any two annotation node
                elements, that is between any combination of <classname><link
                        xlink:href="#tokenization">tok</link></classname>, <classname><link
                        xlink:href="#mark">mark</link></classname> or <classname><link
                        xlink:href="#struct">struct</link></classname>. Unlike <link
                    xlink:href="#struct">hierarchical edges</link>, pointing relations do not
                express 'dominance' semantics, meaning that the source of the edge is not understood
                to 'consist of' the target of the edge. The edge merely marks a relationship between
                two nodes. For this reason, pointing relations are useful in expressing such links
                as coreference (e.g. a link between anaphor and antecedent) and syntactic
                dependencies. Pointing relations are represented using <classname>rel</classname>
                elements in rel files, and obey the definition in <filename>paula_rel.dtd</filename>
                (see <link xlink:href="#DTD">DTDs</link>). The following example illustrates rel
                edges between tokens defined in the file <filename>mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml</filename>,
                but the sources and targets of the edges can also be any
                    <classname>struct</classname> or <classname>mark</classname> within a
                document.</para>
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_PR"><title>Pointing relations between token nodes to annotate dependencies of type "dep"</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_rel.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_dep"/>

<relList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="dep" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml">
    <!-- I - 've -->
    <rel id="rel_1" xlink:href="#tok_1" target="#tok_2"/> 
    <!-- 've - picked -->
    <rel id="rel_2" xlink:href="#tok_3" target="#tok_2"/> 
    <!-- the - kids -->
    <rel id="rel_3" xlink:href="#tok_4" target="#tok_5"/> 
    <!-- picked - kids -->
    <rel id="rel_4" xlink:href="#tok_5" target="#tok_3"/> 
    <!-- picked - up -->
    <rel id="rel_5" xlink:href="#tok_6" target="#tok_3"/> 
</relList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para> The <classname>rel</classname> file only defines the edges and the
                    <classname>@type</classname> of the <classname>relList</classname>, in this case
                "dep". To add an annotation to these edges, for example grammatical functions, a
                    <classname>feat</classname> file is used, as in the following example:</para>
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_PR_feat"><title>Annotating the grammatical function "func" for dependency pointing relations</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_dep_func"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="func" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.dep.xml">
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_1" value="SBJ"/><!-- I - 've -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_2" value="VC"/><!-- 've picked -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_3" value="NMOD"/><!-- the - kids -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_4" value="OBJ"/><!-- picked - kids -->
    <feat xlink:href="#rel_5" value="PRT"/><!-- picked - up -->
</featList>

</paula>
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para> Each <classname>feat</classname> element points to a <classname>rel</classname>
                element in the pointing relation file and gives the annotation value in its
                    <classname>@value</classname> attribute. The name of the annotation, "func", is
                determined in the @type attribute of the <classname>featList</classname>.</para>
            <para>Just as with markables, it is also possible to specify multiple annotations
                for the same pointing relations in one XML document using multiFeat files (see <link
                    xlink:href="#multifeats">multiFeats</link> for details).</para>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="namespaces"><title>Namespaces</title>
            <para>Namespaces in PAULA are user-defined strings that may be used to group together
                XML files belonging to semantically related annotation layers. PAULA namespaces are
                not XML namespaces, but are signaled through a prefix to the file name which by
                convention should contain only alphanumeric ASCII characters and should not begin
                with a number. The end of the prefix is marked by a period. </para>
            <para>As an example, consider the following <link xlink:href="#document"
                    >document's</link> directory structure:</para>
            <para>
                
                <figure xml:id="Figure_paula_dir_ns">
                    <title>Directory structure for a PAULA corpus</title>
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
+-- mycorpus/
¦   +-- doc1/
¦   ¦   ¦-- coref.doc1.discourse.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- coref.doc1.discourse_anaphoric.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.anno.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.annoFeat.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.text.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- syntax.mycorpus.doc1.const.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- syntax.mycorpus.doc1.const_cat.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- syntax.mycorpus.doc1.const_func.xml
... ... ...
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para> The first two file names being with the prefix "coref". This prefix groups them
                together into one namespace, which contains semantically related annotations, such
                as some non-terminal "discourse" nodes, and some annotations or edges defined above
                these nodes, in this case of the type "anaphoric" (for conventional relations
                between node and annotation file names, see <link xlink:href="#naming_conventions"
                    >naming conventions</link>). The last three files begin with "syntax" and belong
                to the corresponding "syntax" namespace. In this case they represent annotations
                such as those seen in the examples in <link xlink:href="#struct">Chapter 7</link>:
                nodes of the type "const", an annotation document of the type "cat" and annother
                annotation called "func", which represents annotated edges between the nodes.
                Finally, the files in the middle begin with the corpus name "mycorpus", which is
                therefore also their namespace. They could also be given a separate namespace (e.g.
                "general.mycorpus...."), but there is no rule prohibiting use of the corpus name as
                a namespace: this will usually be the case when following the <link
                    xlink:href="#naming_conventions">naming conventions</link> if namespaces are not
                intentionally used (then all annotations have the same namespace: the corpus
                name).</para>
            <para>There is no necessary graph-topological connection between annotation layers in
                the same namespace. Often, nodes and their annotations are grouped together using a
                namespace in order to signal their interdependence. However it is entirely possible
                to group any combination of files under one namespace. At present there is no way of
                assigning multiple namespaces to a single file: only the string before the first
                period in a file name is evaluated as its namespace. It is recommended to repeat the
                namespace in the <classname>@paula_id</classname> attribute of each XML file for
                consistency, but the filename itself is the deciding factor in determining the
                namespace.</para>
        </chapter>
        <chapter><title>Special scenarios</title>
        <sect1 xml:id="parallel_corpora">
            <title>Parallel corpora</title>
            <para>Parallel corpora can be modelled in PAULA XML in a variety of ways that are more
                    or less appropriate. For instance, an implicit parallel alignment can be
                    achieved by treating an aligned text as an annotation of a source text (each
                    word or group of words is annotated with parallel words). However, the explicit
                    and recommended representation of parallel corpora in PAULA is modelled by
                    defining multiple <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data">primary text
                            data</link></classname> files within a <classname><link
                            xlink:href="#document">document</link></classname> directory, each with
                    at least one <classname><link xlink:href="#tokenization"
                        >tokenization</link></classname>. In this way, each text is explicitly made
                    independent from the others and text level alignment is represented by the
                    shared document folder. It is recommended to give each text and tokenization a
                    separate, meaningful <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespace</link>, such as
                    the name of the language if dealing with a multilingual parallel corpus.
                    Alignment between elements within parallel texts, including aligned tokens,
                        <link xlink:href="#mark">markable spans</link> (e.g. sentences or chunks) or
                        <link xlink:href="#struct">hierarchical structures</link>, is achieved using
                        <link xlink:href="#pointing_relations">pointing relations</link>. The
                    following example illustrates the document structure and an alignment for some
                    tokens.</para>
            <para>
                
                <figure xml:id="Figure_parallel1">
                    <title>Directory structure for a document with two parallel texts.</title>
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
+-- mycorpus/
¦   +-- doc1/
¦   ¦   ¦-- english.doc1.text.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- english.doc1.tok.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- german.doc1.text.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- german.doc1.tok.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.align.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.anno.xml
... ... ...
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>
                
                <figure xml:id="Figure_parallel2">
                    <title>Pointing relations aligning the English text to the German text.</title>
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_rel.dtd">


<paula version="1.1">

<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_align"/>

<relList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="align">
    <rel id="rel_1" xlink:href="english.doc1.tok.xml#tok_1" 
    target="german.doc.tok.xml#tok_1"/>
    <rel id="rel_1" xlink:href="english.doc1.tok.xml#tok_2" 
    target="german.doc.tok.xml#tok_3"/>
    <rel id="rel_1" xlink:href="english.doc1.tok.xml#tok_3" 
    target="german.doc.tok.xml#tok_2"/>
</paula>
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
                <para>Note that since pointing relations of the same type may not create a cycle,
                    bidirectional alignment is only possible if the pointing relation files are
                    given different types, as in the following example. The two alignment files use
                    the types "align_g-e" and "align_e-g" for each alignment direction.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="Figure_parallel3">
                    <title>Directory structure for a document with bidirectional alignment.</title>
  
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
+-- mycorpus/
¦   +-- doc1/
¦   ¦   ¦-- english.doc1.align_e-g.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- english.doc1.text.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- english.doc1.tok.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- german.doc1.align_g-e.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- german.doc1.text.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- german.doc1.tok.xml
¦   ¦   ¦-- mycorpus.doc1.anno.xml
... ... ...
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 xml:id="dialogue_data">
            <title>Dialogue data</title>
            <para>There are two main ways of representing dialog data in PAULA XML: either each
                    speaker's text and annotations are modeled as a text in a parallel corpus (see
                        <link xlink:href="#parallel_corpora">parallel corpora</link>) or else a
                            <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data">primary textual
                            data</link></classname> file is created with as many blank characters as
                    necessary for the representation of all speakers, and this is then used as a
                    common timeline for the tokens of each speaker. The latter solution is
                    implemented as follows. Supposing two speakers utter the following two semi
                    overlapping sentence:</para>
            <para>
                
                <figure xml:id="Figure_dialog_text">
                    <title>Dialog data to be modelled in PAULA.</title>
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
Speaker1:   he thinks so
Speaker2:              I think so too]]>
              </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>Speaker2 utters the word "I" at the same time as the "o" is uttered in "so" by
                Speaker1. In order to model this overlap using only one "text", the
                <classname>primary textual data</classname> must contain a sufficient amount
                of characters. The text for Speaker1 is 12 characters long, including spaces,
                and the text for Speaker2 begins at character 12 of Speaker1 and extends for a
                further 14 characters. This means we require 25 characters in total (not 26,
                since there is an overlap of one character). The raw text file can therefore
                look like this:</para>
            
            
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_text_dialog"><title>A primary text data file</title><programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_text.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc4_text" type="text"/>

<body>1234567890123456789012345</body>

</paula>]]></programlisting></example>
            </para>
            <para>The body of the text contains repeating numbers: 1234567890... to make it easier
                    to count the characters. However it is equally possible to use 25 spaces: the
                    contents of this dummy text file are not important. In a second step, two
                    tokenizations of the data are carried out: one for each speaker. The
                    tokenization for Speaker1 is given in the following example. It is recommended
                    to give each speaker a separate namespace for easier identifiability. </para>
            
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_dialog_tok"><title>Tokenization for Speaker1</title><programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_mark.dtd">
<paula version="1.1">
                
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc4_tok"/>
                
<markList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="tok" 
xml:base="mycorpus.doc4.text.xml">
 <!-- he -->
 <mark id="tok_1" xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',1,2))"/>
 <!-- thinks -->
 <mark id="tok_2" xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',4,6))"/>
 <!-- so -->
 <mark id="tok_3" xlink:href="#xpointer(string-range(//body,'',11,2))"/>
</markList>

</paula>
            ]]></programlisting></example>
            </para>
            <para>Annotations for each speaker can then be added by refering to the relevant token file and building hierarchical structures above the tokens.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 xml:id="AV_data">
            <title xml:id="multimodal">Aligned audio/video files</title>
            <para>Aligned multimedia files, such as audio or video files, can be added to a PAULA
                    document by placing them in the relevant document directory. In order to specify
                    which part of a text is represented in the aligned file or files, a
                            <classname><link xlink:href="#mark">mark</link></classname> element
                    covering the appropriate span of tokens should be defined and annotated using a
                            <classname><link xlink:href="#feat">feat</link></classname> which
                    contains the file name as in the example below. It is possible to annotate the
                    same <classname>mark</classname> element with multiple multimedia files.</para>
            <para>
                
                <figure xml:id="Figure_AV_seg">
                    <title><emphasis role="italic">A <classname>mark</classname> file defining the
                                span of tokens aligned with a multimedia file</emphasis>.</title>
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_mark.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_audioFileSeg"/>

<markList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="audioFileSeg" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.tok.xml">
 <!-- audio file span for the first 50 tokens -->
 <mark id="audioFileSeg_1" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(id('tok_1')/range-to(id('tok_50')))"/>
</markList>

</paula>
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>
                
                <figure xml:id="Figure_AV_feat">
                    <title>A <classname>feat</classname> file giving the name of the multimedia
                            file.</title>
                    
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id=""mycorpus.doc1_audioFileSeg_audioFile"/>

<featList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="audioFile" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.audioFileSeg.xml">
  <!-- wav file -->
  <feat xlink:href="#audioFileSeg_1" value="file:/./mycorpus.doc1.wav"/>
</featList>

</paula>
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="naming_conventions">
            <title>Naming conventions</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis>General conventions</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>File names in a directory other than the DTDs should ideally contain
                        their corpus path, or at least the document name, i.e. the name of the
                        folder they are in. This ensures that files carry unique names that make
                        them easier to identify. For example, the tokenization file of the document
                            <filename>doc01/</filename> in the corpus <filename>mycorpus</filename>
                        might be called <filename>mycorpus.doc01.tok.xml</filename> or
                            <filename>doc01.tok.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do not use file or folder names with spaces or non-ascii characters.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do not use file or folder names that begin with a number or
                        underscore.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>When using <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespaces</link>, remember
                            that the string before the first period in the file name is construed as
                            the namespace. If you do not wish to use namespaces and follow the file
                            naming conventions given here, the namespace for all of your files will
                            be the corpus name, since files will always be named:
                                <filename>mycorpus.*</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>annoSet, annoFeat, primary text data and tokenization</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <classname><link xlink:href="#annoset">annoSet</link></classname>
                            and, if used, <classname><link xlink:href="#annofeat"
                                >annoFeat</link></classname> files in a document are conventionally
                            named using the document path convention above, with the suffixes
                            anno.xml and anno_feat.xml respectively. For example they can be called:
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc01.anno.xml</filename> and
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc01.anno_feat.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there is only one <classname><link xlink:href="#primary_text_data"
                                    >primary text data</link></classname> file and one <link
                                xlink:href="#tokenization"
                                ><classname>tokenization</classname></link>, they are usually named
                            similarly, but with the suffixes text and tok:
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc01.text.xml</filename> and
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc01.tok.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there are multiple primary text data files or tokenization, their
                            distinguishing features may be used as namespaces, e.g. the name of the
                            language in a <link xlink:href="#parallel_corpora">parallel
                                corpus</link> documents:
                                <filename>english.mycorpus.doc01.text.xml</filename> and
                                <filename>english.mycorpus.doc01.tok.xml</filename>. If the
                            namespaces are already being used for some other purpose (e.g. names of
                            speakers when using a parallel corpus architecture for <link
                                xlink:href="#dialogue_data">dialogue data</link>), suffixes
                            distinguishing text and token files may be used before "text" and "tok",
                            as in: <filename>speaker1.mycorpus.doc01.english.text.xml</filename> and
                                <filename>speaker1.mycorpus.doc01.german.text.xml</filename>, and
                            the same for <filename>*.tok.xml</filename> files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>Anntotation span markables and feature annotations</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By convention, annotation span <link xlink:href="#mark"
                                >markable</link> files are named using the current document name as
                            a prefix, followed by an underscore and the markList's type, followed by
                            "_seg.xml". For example, a markable file that marks text segments
                            corresponding to discourse referents for further annotation may be named
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc01.referent_seg.xml</filename>. This tells us
                            just by looking at the file name that the markable
                                <classname>@type</classname> attribute in the
                                <classname>markList</classname> element is "referent".</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The above file may may also be put in a <link xlink:href="#namespaces"
                                >namespace</link> with some other files relevant to discourse
                            annotation, in which case the files receive a common prefix, e.g. the
                            file could be named:
                                <filename>discourse.mycorpus.doc01.referent_seg.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A feature annotation of the above file giving the referent segment
                            e.g. an annotation called "type" (marking the referent, say, as a person
                            or geopolitical entity), will be given a file name identical to that of
                            the <filename>_seg</filename> file, but with the annotation name
                            appended after a further underscore:
                                <filename>discourse.mycorpus.doc01.referent_seg_type.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>Hierarchical struct nodes and feature annotations</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Hierarchical <link xlink:href="#struct"
                                ><classname>struct</classname></link> nodes are placed in files
                            using the same general conventions with regard to namespaces and
                            corpus/document path above, and carry a suffix corresponding to the
                                <classname>@type</classname> attribute in the
                                <classname>structList</classname> element after an underscore, as
                            follows. For nodes annotating syntactic constituents of the type "const"
                            within the <link xlink:href="#namespaces">namespace</link> "syntax" we
                            may get a file called:
                                <filename>syntax.mycorpus.doc01.const.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Annotations of struct nodes are given the same name as the
                            corresponding node file, with a suffix consisting of an underscore and
                            the annotation's name from the <classname>@type</classname> attribute of
                            the <classname>featList</classname> element. For example, an annotation
                            of the above constituent nodes giving the syntactic category called
                            "cat" should be named:
                                <filename>syntax.mycorpus.doc01.const_cat.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Feature annotations of edges in the same <classname>struct</classname>
                            file should be named using the same convention, e.g. a syntactic
                            function annotation of the type "func" may be called:
                                <filename>syntax.mycorpus.doc01.const_func.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>Pointing relations and rel annotations</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><link xlink:href="#pointing_relations">Pointing relation</link> files
                            are named using the same conventions as above, with the edge type used
                            as a suffix after the document name, e.g. a coreference edge file of the
                            type "coref" in the discourse <link xlink:href="#namespaces"
                                >namespace</link> should be named:
                                <filename>discourse.mycorpus.doc01.coref.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Feature annotations of pointing relation edges are given the file name
                            of the pointing relation file with an underscore and the annotation type
                            as a suffix. For example, annotating the "coref" edge above with the
                            annotation "type" (e.g. anaphoric or appositional) results in the file
                            name:
                            <filename>discourse.mycorpus.doc01.coref_type.xml</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>multiFeat annotations</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A <classname>mutliFeat</classname> file has no single annotation type.
                            It is therefore usually named using the name of the file to which it
                            adds annotations, with the suffix "_multiFeat". Therefore the name of a
                                <classname>multiFeat</classname> file annotation a token file is
                            e.g. <classname>mycorpus.doc1.tok_multiFeat.xml</classname>, a
                                <classname>multiFeat</classname> file annotating syntactic
                            constituents called "const" might be called
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc1.const_multiFeat.xml</filename>, etc. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>For metadata multiFeat annotations, usually the document path and the
                            suffix "meta_multiFeat" are used, e.g.
                                <classname>mycorpus.doc1.meta_multiFeat.xml</classname>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>The paula_id attribute</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <classname>@paula_id</classname> attribute of the
                                <classname>header</classname> element in each filed should be named
                            like the file name itself without the .xml extension, e.g. the paula_id
                            of <filename>mycorpus.doc01.tok.xml</filename> might be
                                <filename>mycorpus.doc01.tok</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the resulting name has no suffix containing an underscore, it is
                            possible to replace the final period in the file name with an
                            underscore, e.g. <filename>mycorpus.doc01_tok</filename>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="versions">
        <title>Older versions and deprecated components</title>
        <sect1>
            <title>Pointing relations in feats</title>
            <para> Up to PAULA XML version 1.0 it was possible to create <link
                    xlink:href="#pointing_relations">pointing relations</link> by assigning a
                feature annotation to a source node with the target node's URI as a feature value
                (in PAULA 0.9 only) or using the now deprecated <classname>@target</classname>
                attribute of the feat element (from PAULA 1.0). The use of
                    <classname>@value</classname> for this purpose is illustrated in the example
                below.</para>
            <para>
                <example xml:id="Example_feat_PR">
                    <title>A deprecated pointing relation <classname>Feat</classname> file.</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_feat.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
 <header paula_id="mycorpus.doc1_coref" />
 <featList type="coref" xml:base="mycorpus.doc1.referent_Seg.xml" 
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <feat xlink:href="#referent_10" value="#referent_8" />
 </featList>

</paula>]]></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>The problem with this structure is that it is not unambiguously clear that the
                annotation signifies a pointing relation, rather than a label annotation that
                happens to resemble a URI (an annotation with the string value "#referent_8" in the
                example above). As of PAULA 1.1, <classname>rel</classname> files with their
                corresponding DTD should be used to define pointing relations, making the
                identification of source and target nodes unambiguous. It is still possible (though
                deprecated) to use a <classname>feat</classname> file for this purpose, as long as
                the pointing relation's target is marked using <classname>@target</classname>
                instead of <classname>@value</classname>. However, this will not be supported in
                future versions of the PAULA standard.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
            <title xml:id="virtual_markables">Virtual markables</title>
            <para> In PAULA XML version 0.9 it was possible to define "virtual markables" which
                could span several <link xlink:href="#mark">markables</link>, either in the same
                markable file or in any number of different markable files applying to the same
                tokenization. The following example illustrates such a file, where the virtual
                markable, designated by the <classname>@type</classname> "virtual", refers to two
                markables within the same file (the path
                    <filename>mycorpus.doc5.referentSeg.xml</filename> must be specified since
                    <classname>@xml:base</classname> is set to a separate tokenization file). </para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="Figure_virtual_marks">
                    <title><emphasis role="italic">A <classname>mark</classname> file containing a
                            pseudo-hierarchical markable of the deprecated "virtual"
                        type</emphasis>.</title>
                    <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE paula SYSTEM "paula_mark.dtd">

<paula version="1.1">
<header paula_id="mycorpus.doc5_referentSeg"/>

<markList xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
type="referent" xml:base="mycorpus.doc5.tok.xml">
 <!-- audio file span for the first 50 tokens -->
 <mark id="referentSeg_1" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(id('tok_1')/range-to(id('tok_2')))"/>
 <mark id="referentSeg_2" 
  xlink:href="#xpointer(id('tok_5')/range-to(id('tok_8')))"/>
 <mark id="referentVirt_1"
  xlink:href="(mycorpus.doc5.referentSeg.xml#referentSeg_1,
  mycorpus.doc5.referentSeg.xml#referentSeg_2)" type="virtual"/>
</markList>

</paula>
]]>
                            </programlisting>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>Though virtual markables technically appear to be hierarchical structures by
                pointing at constituent markables, they are interpreted as flat spans which apply to
                exactly the same tokens as those covered by the constituent markables. Therefore the
                virtual markable in the example above is the same as a markable applying to tokens
                1-2 and 5-8. The use of virtual markables has been deprecated and is no longer part
                of the current PAULA XML standard. Note that it is possible to create discontinuous
                spans using normal markables, by specifying discontinous ranges of tokens in the
                    <classname>@xlink:href</classname> attribute.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
            <title>Synopsis of older PAULA versions and components</title>
            <para>This section lists distinctive characteristics of the different PAULA XML standard
                versions to date. </para>
            <para><emphasis>Version 0.9</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <link xlink:href="#virtual_markables">virtual markables</link>
                            is possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname>feat</classname> attribute
                                <classname>@value</classname> to specify <link
                                xlink:href="#pointing_relations">pointing relation</link> target
                            nodes is possible/</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>No support for <link xlink:href="#metadata">metadata</link>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname><link xlink:href="#annofeat"
                                >annoFeat</link></classname> is mandatory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis>Version 1.0</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of virtual markables is no longer possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname>feat</classname> attribute
                                <classname>@value</classname> or <classname>@target</classname> to
                            specify pointing relation target nodes is possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>No support for metadata.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname>annoFeat</classname> is mandatory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist><emphasis>Version 1.1</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of virtual markables is not possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname>feat</classname> attribute
                                <classname>@value</classname> to specify pointing relation target
                            nodes is not possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname>feat</classname> attribute
                                <classname>@target</classname> to specify pointing relation target
                            nodes is possible but deprecated.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>New file type and element <classname>rel</classname> is recommended
                            for the specification of pointing relations.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Support for metadata on the corpus, subcorpus and document
                            levels.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use of <classname>annoFeat</classname> is optional and
                            deprecated.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Support for <link xlink:href="#parallel_corpora">parallel
                                corpora</link> via pointing relations.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Support for aligned <link xlink:href="#multimodal">multimedia
                                files</link>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </sect1>
    </chapter>
     <bibliography xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'>
        <title>References</title>
        
        <bibliomixed>
            <bibliomset relation="journal"><abbrev>ChiarcosEtAl2008</abbrev>Chiarcos, C., Dipper, S., Götze, M., Leser, U., Lüdeling,
                A., Ritz, J. &amp; Stede, M. (2008), A Flexible Framework for Integrating
                Annotations from Different Tools and Tag Sets. <title>Traitment automatique des
                    langues</title>
                <volumenum>49</volumenum>, <pagenums>271-293</pagenums>. </bibliomset> 
        </bibliomixed>
         <bibliomixed>
            <bibliomset relation="proceedings"><abbrev>Dipper2005</abbrev>Dipper, S. (2005), XML-based Stand-off Representation and Exploitation of Multi-Level Linguistic Annotation. In: <title role="proceedings">Proceedings of Berliner XML Tage
                    2005 (BXML 2005)</title>. Berlin, Germany, <pagenums>39-50</pagenums>. 
            </bibliomset>
         </bibliomixed>
         <bibliomixed>
            <bibliomset relation="proceedings"><abbrev>DipperGoetze2005</abbrev>Dipper, S. &amp; Götze, M. (2005), Accessing Heterogeneous Linguistic Data - Generic XML-based Representation and Flexible Visualization
                . In: <title role="proceedings">Proceedings of the 2nd Language &amp; Technology Conference: Human Language Technologies as a Challenge for Computer Science and Linguistics</title>. Poznan, Poland, <pagenums>206-210</pagenums>. 
            </bibliomset>
            
         </bibliomixed>
        
    </bibliography>
</book>
